

CONTACT

- ARIES Observatory
 Nainital-263001
 Uttarkhand, India
- +91 5942-270-704
- bibhuti@aries.res.in
- https://bibhuraushan.github.io

RESEARCH SKILLS

Image Processing

Image restoration, feature identification, feature tracking and other processing in the historical and modern space based solar images.

• Numerical Techniques

Roots finding, differentiation, integration, solution of multidimensional linear equations, solution of differential equations, etc. Familiar with 2D kinematic dynamo code **SURYA** developed by Prof. Arnab Rai Choudhuri and his students.

Data Statistics

Descriptive and Inferential statistics (Frequentist and Bayesian Inferences), etc.

• Machine Learning

Linear Regression, classification (K-means clustering), Feature identification based on ML & Al (beginner)

BIBHUTI KUMAR JHA

Post Doctoral Fellow ARIES, Nainital

AREA OF RESEARCH

My primary area of research is Solar Astrophysics. I work on century-long archived data obtained at the different ground and space-based observatories to understand the long-term variation in the Sun. I work on the development of automatic algorithms using various image processing and mathematical techniques to extract solar magnetic features from digital images. Then, I study and analyse the physical parameters extracted from these features to understand the physics underneath. In addition, I am also interested in the Solar Dynamo theory to understand the magnetic cycle of the Sun. Moreover, I am also willing to expand my understanding of the various exciting phenomena happening in the solar atmosphere.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

- Post Doctoral Fellow (PDF) Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital; (Sep 2022 on wards)
- Post Doctoral Researcher (PDR) Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital; (Feb 2022 – Sep 2022)
- Research Fellow Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore & Aryabhatta Research Institute of Observational Sciences (ARIES), Nainital; (Jan 2017 – Jan 2022)

EDUCATION

Ph.D. (Solar Astrophysics): Indian Institute of Astrophysics (IIA), Bangalore (Registered with Pondicherry University, Puducherry); (2017–2022)

Thesis Title: Long-term study of the Sun and its implications to solar dynamo models

Thesis Supervisor: Prof. Dipankar Banerjee

- M.Sc. (Physics): Department of Physics & Astrophysics, Hindu College, University of Delhi, New Delhi, India; (2014–2016)
- **B.Sc. (Physics):** Dyal Singh College, University of Delhi, New Delhi, India; **(2011–2014)**

PUBLICATIONS

- Extending the Sunspot Area Series from Kodaikanal Solar Observatory Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Manjunath Hegade, Aditya Priyadarshi, Sudip Mandal & Dipankar Banerjee, Frontiers In Astronomy And Space Sciences (2022)
- A theoretical model of the near-surface shear layer of the Sun Bibhuti Kumar Jha & Arnab Rai Choudhuri: MNRAS (2021) 506:2 (2189)

COMPUTER SKILLS

C, C++	10+ yrs
IDL, Python	5+ yrs
R, Rust, Julia	2+ yrs
Mathematica, Fortran	2+ yrs
LaTex, Html/CSS	5+ yrs
Adobe Photoshop	9+ yrs
Adobe Lightroom	3+ yrs
InkScape	2+ yrs

PROFILES

- % NASA ADS
- Google Scholar
- ArXive
- ORCID
- ResearchGate

 Measurements of Solar Differential Rotation Using the Century Long Kodaikanal Sunspot Data

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Aditya Priyadarshi, Sudip Mandal, Subhamoy Chatterjee & Dipankar Banerjee; *Sol Phys (2021) 296: 25*

- Magnetic field dependence of bipolar magnetic region tilts on the Sun: Indication of tilt quenching
 - Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Bidya Binay Karak, Sudip Mandal, Dipankar Banerjee; *APjL (2020) 889:L19*
- Delving into the Historical Ca II K Archive from the Kodaikanal Observatory: the Potential of the Most Recent Digitised Series

Theodosios Chatzistergos, Ilaria Ermolli, Sami K. Solanki, Natalie A. Krivova, Dipankar Banerjee, Bibhuti K. Jha, Subhamoy Chatterjee; *Sol Phys (2019)* 294: 145

 Study of Sunspot Penumbra to Umbra Area Ratio Using Kodaikanal Whitelight Digitised Data

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Sudip Mandal, & Dipankar Banerjee, *Sol Phys (2019)* 294: 72

PROCEEDINGS

 Long-term variation of sunspot penumbra to umbra ratio: A study using Kodaikanal white-light digitized data

Bibhuti Kumar Jha, Sudip Mandal, & Dipankar Banerjee 2018, *Proceedings of the International Astronomical*, *Union*, 13, 185–186

CONFERENCES AND MEETINGS

- Presented a e-talk titled Signature of tilt quenching from observation of tilted bipolar magnetic regions on the Sun, in 31st International Astronomical Union General Assembly (IAUGA) 2022, 2-11 August 2022, Busan, South Korea
- Presented a talk titled Update on Ca-K data from Kodaikanal Solar Observatory, Workshop on "Long-term study of the solar activity" in the 40th Astronomical Society of India Meeting, 25-29 March, 2022
- Presented a poster titled A Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun, The 40th Astronomical Society of India Meeting, 25-29 March, 2022
- Presented a talk titled A Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun, The 15th Quadrennial Solar-Terrestrial Physics (STP-15) symposium, 21-25 February, 2022, Online
- Presented a e-poster titled A Theoretical Model of the Near-Surface Shear Layer of the Sun, The 16th European Solar Physics Meetings (ESPM-16), 6-10 September, 2021, Online
- Presented a talk titled Signature of quenching from observation of tilted bipolar magnetic regions on the Sun, IIA-50 Conference - Advances in Observations and Modelling of Solar Magnetism and Variability, 1-4 March, 2021, IIA, Bangalore, India
- Presented a talk titled Magnetic field dependence of bipolar magnetic region tilts on the Sun: Evidence of tilt quenching, Astronomical Society of India Meeting 2020, 13-17 February, 2020, IISER Tirupati, India
- Presented a poster titled Solar differential rotation as measured from century long Kodaikanal white light digitized data, 5th Asia Pacific Solar Physics Meeting (APSPM), 3-7 February, IUCAA, Pune, India
- Presented a poster titled Magnetic field dependency of bipolar magnetic region tilt angle: A study using MDI and HMI data sets, IRIS-10, 4-8 November, 2019, Christ University Bangalore, India

OTHER SKILLS

Photography

Apart from my research work photography is the area where I spend most of my time.

- Presented a poster titled Solar Differential Rotation in last century: A study from Kodaikanal white light digitised data, Young Astronomers Meet, 23-27 September, 2019, Kodaikanal Solar Observatory, IIA Kodaikanal, India
- Attended Solar Physics Summer School at Raman Science Center,10 -16 June, 2019, Leh, India
- Presented an oral talk titled An update on Kodaikanal Digital Archived
 Data in a meeting entitled "Reconstructing Solar and Heliospheric Magnetic Field Evolution Over the Past Century", ISSI Team led by Alexei Pevtsov; 12 15 February, 2019
- Presented an oral talk titled Magnetic field dependency of Bipolar magnetic region tilt angle: A study from SOHO/MDI data, Young Astronomers Meet, 24-28 September, 2018, PRL, Ahmadabad, India
- Presented a poster titled Long-term variation of sunspot penumbra to umbra ratio: A study using Kodaikanal white-light digitized data., IAUS-340, 19 - 24 February, 2018, Jaipur, India

VISITS

- Visiting Scholar at Indian Institute of Technology (IIT), Banaras Hindu University (BHU), Varanasi, India; December 2018
- Visiting Scholar at Max Planck Institute for Solar System Research, Göttingen, Germany; Feb May, 2019

FELLOWSHIPS AND AWARDS

- Awarded with Council Of Scientific And Industrial Research (CSIR), Junior Research Fellowship (NET-JRF), 2017
- Selected for Heliophysics Summer School, 23 20 July, 2018 Boulder, Colorado, USA; Under NASA Living With Star (LWS) program

MEMBERSHIP

· Lifetime member of Astronomical Society of India.

PARTIAL GUIDANCE

- Tanushree Bhattacharya; Currently a BS-MS student at Indian Association for the Cultivation of Science, Kolkata, India; (NIUS Student)
- Aditya Priyadarshi; Former BS-MS student at Indian Institute of Science Education and Research, Kolkata; (Master Thesis)
- Anu Sridevi; Currently a PhD student at Indian Institute of Technology (BHU), Varanasi, India
- · Dibya Kirti Mishra; Currently a PhD student at ARIES Nainital, India

OTHER RESPONSIBILITIES

- Organised a workshop in 40th Astronomical Society of India annual meeting 2022 titled "Long-term Study of Solar Activity."
- Active role in the organisation of ARIES E-lecture series 2020.